Finding Aid for Humphry and Moses Marshall Papers
William L. Clements Library, University of Michigan
- Correspondence, Writings, and Documents
  - Humphry Marshall ALS Copy to [John Coakley] Lettsom, May 7, 1788, Marshall sends four tortoises. Remarks on the dietary preferences of tortoises. Descriptions of new species of Sedum, Portulacaea, and an evergreen to be named Lettsomaea
  - John Strode ALS to Humphry Marshall, June 20, 1788, The search for Andromeda arborea continues
  - Samuel Kramsch ALS to Humphry Marshall (1722-1801), July 2, 1788, Favorable comments on "Arbustrum Americanum". Kramsch encourages Marshall to complete the volume on hebaceous plants of North America
  - [Moses Marshall] AL to Hannah Buffington, September 30, 1788, Re: estate of Grandfather Waits
  - James Kenny ALS to Humphry Marshall, February 10, 1789, Comments on Erasmus' paraphrase of Matthew respecting paying tribute to Casear
  - R[ichar]d Bennett ALS to Humphry Marshall, February 24, 1789, Thanks for plants received
  - Samuel Kramsch ALS to Humphry Marshall, July 25, 1789, Kramsch is surprised by the lack of encouragement to prepare a volume on the herbaceous plants of North America and by the slow sales of "Arbustrum"
  - Thomas Parke ALS to Humphry Marshall, August 17, 1789
  - J[ames?] Ross ALS to Humphry Marshall, September 21, 1789, Re: attempts to divide Chester County
  - James M. Watson ALS to Humphry Marshall, December 10, 1789, Acknowledgement of receipt of plants and seeds. "List of Seeds & plants of Flowering Trees Shrubs Evergreens &c. Bot of James Watson" (Box 2)
  - Rich[ar]d Burnett ALS to Humphry Marshall, January 15, 1790, List of plants Burnett does and does not wish to receive
  - [Thomas] Parke ANS to Humphry Marshall, January 20, 1790
  - Geo[rge] Baker ALS to Humphry Marshall, January 26, 1790.
  - Samuel Kramsh ALS to Humphry Marshall, February 20, 1790
  - R[ichar]d Burnett ALS to Humphry Marshall, March 2, 1790, Payment for most recent shipment of plants. Seeks Magnolia, Liriodendron, and Kalmia more than 'a great number of insignificant little shrubs'
  - Jean Reichert ALS to [Humphry Marshall], March 6, 1790, and Grommee & Co. ALS to Humphry Marshall, April 1790, Receipt of shipment and new order. Grommee & Co. (the intermediaries) provide a translation of Reichert's letter
  - Thomas Parke ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], March 20, 1790
  - Baker & Abel ALS to Moses Marshall, May 17, 1790, Have sold some gin for Marshall
  - Sarah Arnold ADS, June 16, 1790, Sarah Arnold's will.
  - James M. Watson ALS to Hum[phr]y Marshall, July 27, 1790, Offers services to collect plants
  - Robert Barclay ALS extract to [Thomas] Parke, July 1790, Order for plants for John Mackie and Lord Suffield to be filled by Humphry Marshall
  - John Gordon ALS to Humphry Marshall, August 14, 1790, Order for forest trees and other plants to be used for 'experiment and amusement'
  - J. Cockfield ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], August 24, 1790
  - T[homas] Parke ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], October 19, 1790, Order for plants for Drs. Pitcairn and Orne
  - Thomas Parke ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], October 26, 1790
  - Moses Marshall ADfS to Jos[eph] Banks, October 30, 1790, and Moses Marshall ADfS to Gent[leme]n, [ca. October 30, 1790], Fulfillment of Banks' order; Mention of Marshall's 'botanic tour' through the Appalachians; Discovery of wild Franklinia alatamaha; Mention of the 'botanic tour'
  - Thomas Parke ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], November 6, 1790, Shipment forwarded to Banks
  - James M. Watson ALS to Moses Marshall, November 6, 1790, List of plants and seeds collected for the Marshalls
  - Manuscript Note, [ca. 1790], Transcription of Benjamin Franklin's epitaph and notes on his bequest
  - R[ichar]d Burnett ALS to Hump[hr]y Marshall, April 13, 1791, The last shipment of plants was destroyed in transit
  - Steph[e]n Girard ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], August 11, 1791, Order for plants from a 'Gentleman in Paris'
  - J. Cockfield ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], August 23, 1791
  - Thomas Parke ALS to Moses Marshall, October 5, 1791
  - Tho[ma]s Parke ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], October 7, 1791, Bond requests 4 boxes of ornamental shrubs for his 'Gentleman's garden'
  - Steph[e]n Girard ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], October 29, 1791
  - [Moses Marshall] Letterbook, November 10, 1791 - November 28, 1791
  - John Sellers ALS to Humphry Marshall, February 2, 1792, News on a proposed road through southeastern Pennsylvania being discussed in the Pennsylvania legislature
  - A[rchibald] Thomson ALS to Humphry Marshall, March 26, 1792, Large order for plants
  - Thomas Parke ALS to M[oses] Marshall, May 2, 1792, Eddy vs. Turner
  - Caspar Wistar, Jr. ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], May 27, 1792, Control of the Hessian Fly; Letter written on printed circular soliciting information on the Hessian Fly
  - T[homas] Parke ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], June 13, 1792
  - Caspar Wistar, Jr. ALS to [Moses] Marshall or Humphry Marshall, June 20, 1792, Information on a proposed expedition to explore the West
  - Thomas Parke ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], September 11, 1792
  - Tho[mas] Parke ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], September 18, 1792
  - Geo[rge] Baker ALS to Moses Marshall, December 21, 1792, Burnett's order has been sent
  - Tim[oth]y Hurst ALS to Moses Marshall, August 5, 1793, Will assist in collecting ginseng
  - Tho[ma]s Parke ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], November 7, 1793, Order for plants. Yellow Fever epidemic is ended
  - Moses Marshall Letterbook, December 11, 1793 - December 12, 1793
  - Archi[bald] Thomson ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], June 4, 1794, Large order for plants
  - "Person in Liverpool" ALS Copy to "Friend in New York", September 1, 1794, Story of Sarah Harrison's meeting the King of England
  - Thomas Fisher ALS to Moses Marshall, January 27, 1795, Estate of Jas. Gibbons
  - Reg[inald] Whitley ALS to Humphry Marshall, May 17, 1795, Introduces himself and request plants
  - Reginald Whitley ALS to Moses Marshall, July 1, 1795, with M[oses] M[arshall] ALS to Reginald Whitley, [1795]
  - Reg[inald] Whitley ALS to Moses Marshall, May 3, 1796, Large order for plants
  - Samuel Bard ALS to Humphry Marshall, June 24, 1796
  - Samuel Bard ALS to Moses Marshall, September 10, 1796, Order for ornamental plants
  - John Dickinson ALS to Humphry Marshall, November 1, 1796
  - Thomas Parke ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], January 31, 1797
  - John Dickinson ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], July 31, 1797
  - John Dickinson ALS to Moses Marshall, November 7, 1797
  - Milling Account Book, March 20, 1799 - September 9, 1808
  - Thomas Parke ANS to Moses Marshall, August 3, 1799
  - Thomas Parke ANS to Moses Marshall, September 21, 1799, Re: delayed order of plants to be sent to Britain
  - Baron Itzenplitz ALS to Moses Marshall, November 18, 1799, Order for plants and seeds
  - Roger Dicks ALS to Humphry Marshall, February 6, 1800, Eye surgery might help Marshall's cataracts
  - C[aspar] Wistar, Jr. ALS to Humphrey Marshall [Humphry Marshall], April 11, 1800, Recommends Marshall remain on his diet until surgery
  - Humphry Marshall ALS to "Respected Friend", May 13, 1800, and Sarah Marshall ADS, [ca. 1800], Receipt for salve
  - C[aspar] Wistar, Jr. ALS to Humphry Marshall, May 16, 1800, Suggestions on post-operative care
  - A[rchibald] Thomson ALS to Humphry Marshall, May 28, 1800, Order for plants and seeds
  - Thomas Parke ALS to Moses Marshall, September 13, 1800, Order for seeds for British client
  - Mathias King ALS to Humphry Marshall, November 9, 1800, Order for plants
  - John Romans and Mary Smith ADS, July 23, 1801, Marriage Certificate.
  - Moses Marshall ADS Copy to Jacob Dinger and William Lollar, November 17, 1801
  - James Mease ALS to Moses Marshall, February 2, 1802, Thanks Marshall for his promise to assist with horticultural articles in Mease's forthcoming encyclopedia
  - J. Allison D[ ] Partially Printed DS Fragment to Moses Marshall, November 30, 1801, Names Marshall executor of an estate
  - James Mease ALS to Moses Marshall, January 3, 1803, Prospects for his 'Domestic Encyclopedia'. Death of Humphry Marshall
  - James Mease ALS to Moses Marshall, January 19, 1803, Wishes to publish Humphry Marshall's notes on herbaceous American plants, if such exist
  - Moses Marshall ALS Copy to James Mease, February 10, 1803, Marshall, being busy with his grist mill, cannot assist much with Mease's requests; Humphry Marshall's notes not likely to provide much useful information
  - James Mease ALS to Moses Marshall, March 22, 1803, Intends to name a new genus Marshallia in honor of Marshall
  - James Mease ALS to Moses Marshall, April 13, 1803, Comments on botanical matters, including Barton's "Elements of Botany"
  - Mathias King ALS to [Moses] Marshall, July 13, [1803?], Description of a botanical tour in the Poconos (?)
  - Mathias King ALS to Moses Marshall, August 24, 1803, King can provide plants from Florida
  - James Mease ALS to Moses Marshall, September 1, 1803, Wishes to obtain a specimen of the oil nut. How to propagate plants.
  - Manuscript Document Copy, "Courses & Distances of the Strasburgh road...", June 18, 1804, "Courses & Distances of the Strasburgh road from W. Chester to Strasburgh"
  - Manuscript Document Copy, "General Directions to the Administrators of Jonathan Matlock, deceased", April 11, 1805
  - James Mease ALS to Moses Marshall, September 11, 1806, Seeks information on a threshing machine seen at T. Coxe's
  - [Unidentified shoemaker's] Account Book, January 1809 - February 1815
  - Richard Marshall ALS to Moses Marshall, May 6, 1812, Legal and financial trouble
  - [Moses Marshall] Account Book, December 17, 1812 - September 15, 1813
  - Samuel Butler ADS Copy to Margaret Arnold, April 4, 1830, Life-time lease of property to Margaret Arnold (Box 3)
  - M[aria] W. Marshall ALS to Moses Marshall, April 10, 1830, News of family and friends; John Pim 'has started toward the Western country'. Samuel Peirce is 'making his usual fall collection of Seeds & plants'
  - [Moses Marshall?] Account Book, January 1829 - March 4, 1831, Personal expenditures of Moses Marshall while in Philadelphia studying medicine
  - Humphry Marshall, Aquila Marshall, Townsend Samborn, and James Jefferies Partially Printed DS to Maria Marshall, July 30, 1832, "Bond…in the penalty of $16602.74 Conditioned for the payment of her distributive share in Lot No. 1"
  - [Eliza Gause] AL to Caroline E. Baily [Marshall], December 19, 1834, Account of daily activities
  - Caroline E. [Baily] Marshall ADS Copy, September 8, 1838, Caroline E. Marshall's will.
  - John Nelson ADS Copy, May 15, 1840, Survey of plot of land on the Susquehanna River
  - [Moses Marshall] Manuscript Copy, "Pains Political", [ca. 1845]
  - George Rich[ar]d Baker ALS to Moses Marshall, February 6, 1847, Inquiry into establishing an almshouse
  - Moses Marshall ALS Copy to William Darlington, December 25, 1847, Regarding a memorial to Humphry and Moses Marshall
  - Moses Marshall ALS to William Richardson, December 30, 1847
  - [Moses Marshall] ADf. to [William Darlington], [before May 17, 1848], Notes on the lives of Humphry and Moses Marshall
  - [Moses Marshall] 6 ADfs. to [William Darlington], May 17, 1848, Drafts with information on the lives of Humphry and Moses Marshall
  - Moses Marshall ALS Copy to John Fisher, December 29, 1848, Regarding rental property
  - W[illia]m Darlington ALS to [Moses Marshall], March 9, 1849, Regarding Memorial of John Bartram and Humphry Marshall
  - William Richardson ALS to [Moses] Marshall, March 23, 1849, Rental of lime kilns
  - W[illia]m Darlington ALS to John Bohlen, September 10, 1849, List of plants still growing in Humphry Marshall's garden
  - W[illia]m Darlington ALS to Moses Marshall, December 25, 1849, Wishes to see two letters from Franklin written to Marshall (March 18, 1770, and April 22, 1771)
  - Manuscript Biographies of John Bartram, Humphry and Moses Marshall, and William Baldwin, [ca. 1849], Biographies of John Bartram, Humphry and Moses Marshall, and William Baldwin
  - Moses Marshall ALS Copy to James Slaughter, November 30, 1850, Dispute over property sold by John Fisher
  - William Richardson ALS to Moses Marshall, May 1, 1851, Regarding taxes on 'the ferry property'
  - Moses Marshall DS to [Joel C. Baily], October 16, 1851, with Joel C. Baily ADS to [Moses Marshall], October 17, 1851
  - William Richardson ALS to [Moses] Marshall, October 23, 1854, and Moses Marshall ALS Copy to William Richardson, November 6, 1854
  - W[illia]m Richardson ALS to [Moses Marshall], March 14, 1855, Hard winter. Smallpox epidemic has not affected Richardson's family because they were inoculated
  - W[illia]m Richardson ALS to [Moses] Marshall, January 4, 1856
  - W[illia]m Richardson ALS to Moses Marshall, August 4, 1856
  - William Richardson ALS to M[oses] Marshall, November 21, 1856
  - W[illia]m Richardson ALS to M[oses] Marshall, December 15, 1856
  - W[illia]m Darlington ALS to M[oses] Marshall, November 16, 1861, Mrs. James, preparing biological sketches of botanists, wishes to reproduce facsimiles of some letters in Marshall's posession
  - [Moses Marshall?] ADf., [Against Suspension of Writ of Habeas Corpus], [1861], Diatribe against suspension of writ of habeas corpus
  - James J. Levick ALS to Elizabeth W. Levick and Mary Levick, with silhouette of James J. Levick, September 20, 1862, Includes Peale Museum silhouette of James J. Levick, 1840
  - [Moses Marshall] ADf., [Secession and Politics], [1863], Resolution on the right for Southern states to secede. Support of the candidacies of George W. Woodward for Governor and Walter Lowrey for Supreme Court
  - [Moses Marshall] ADf., [Pro-Southern Diatribe], [1863], Pro-Southern diatribe.
  - [Moses Marshall] ADf., [Political Parties, Slavery, and Wage Labor], [1863], Discussion of political parties, slavery, and wage labor
  - Manuscript Genealogical Chart of the Marshall Family, Undated, Genealogical chart of Marshall family
  - Manuscript Diary Pages, Undated, Visit to Dr. Squibb
  - Lloyd, Peter Z. ANS to Humphry Marshall, May 10
  - [Marshall, Moses] AMs., "Apoplexia", Undated, "Apoplexia"
  - [Marshall, Moses] AMs., "The Brandywine Railroad", Undated, "The Brandywine Railroad"
  - [Marshall, Moses] AMs., [Chemistry Lecture Notes], Undated, Chemistry lecture notes
  - [Marshall, Moses] AL to Unknown Recipient, Undated, and Unidentified Writer AMs. Poem, Undated, Receipt for kidney ailment
  - Squibb, R[obert] ALS to [Humphry] Marshall, Undated, Squibb is collecting plants to fill an order for Mr. DeBrahm
  - Squibb, Rob[er]t ALS to Humphry Marshall, August 14, Request for lettuce
- Poetry (Box 3)
  - Manuscript Poetry, [18th-19th century], Poetry by multiple writers, in multiple hands.
- Bound and Printed Items (Box 3)
  - Jacob Martin Arithmetic Notebook, March 10, 1856 - June 20, 1856
  - Jacob Martin Arithmetic Notebook, September 1, 1856 - October 17, 1856
  - William Darlington Manuscript, "Historical introduction to Bartram & Marshall", Undated
  - John Milleson Account and Memorandum Book, November 3, 1846 - April 3, 1848
  - Arbustrum Americanum, Uncut Sheets, [1785]
  - Other published works, 7 items
    See separated materials section of this finding aid for a complete list of these publications.
Items located in the Book Division of the Clements Library:
Anno regni Georgii III. Regis, Magnae Britanniae, Franciae & Hiberniae, decimo tertio.: At a General Assembly of the province of Pennsylvania, begun and holden at Philadelphia, the fourteenth day of October, anno Domini 1772 ... And from thence continued by adjournments to the twenty-sixth day of February, 1773. Philadelphia: Printed and sold by Hall and Sellers, at the new printing-office, near the market, 1773.
Darlington, William, and H. Fennell. Florula cestrica:: an essay towards a catalogue of the phaenogamous plants, native and naturalized, growing in the vicinity of the borough of West-Chester, in Chester County, Pennsylvania: with brief notices of their properties, and uses, in medicine, rural economy, and the arts.: To which is subjoined an appendix of the useful cultivated plants of the same district.... West-Chester, Penn.: Printed for the author, by Simeon Siegfried, 1826.
Dover, William. Useful miscellanies: or, Serious reflections, respecting mens duty to God, and one toward another: With advices, civil and religious, tending to regulate their conduct in the various occurrences of human life. Published for general service, by a well-wisher to all mankind.... London: printed for T. Cooper, 1739.
Ellis, John, and Simon Taylor. An historical account of coffee: with an engraving, and botanical description of the tree: to which are added sundry papers relative to its culture and use, as an article of diet and of commerce. London: Printed for Edward and Charles Dilly, 1774.
Lettsom, J. Coakley. The natural history of the tea-tree: with observations on the medical qualities of tea, and effects of tea-drinking.... London: Printed for E. and C. Dilly, 1772.
Marshall, Humphry. Arbustrum Americanum: the American grove, or, An alphabetical catalogue of forest trees and shrubs, natives of the American United States, arranged according to the Linnæan system ...: also, some hints of their uses in medicine, dyes, and domestic oeconomy. Philadelphia: Printed by Joseph Crukshank, 1785.
Randall, Joseph. A system of geography: or, A dissertation on the creation and various phænomena of the terraqueous globe .... London: Printed for Joseph Lord, bookseller, in Wakefield, and sold by him... and J. Rivington..., 1744.
The Clements Library's Wayne papers contain a letter by Humphry Marshall: Humphry Marshall to A[nthony] Wayne, May 16, 1790.
The University of Michigan holds copies of both Arbustrum Americanum and its French translation (search the University's online catalog).
Marshall papers at other repositories include: Humphry Marshall papers, Special Collections, National Agricultural Library.
Darlington, William, and Peter Collinson. Memorials of John Bartram and Humphry Marshall: with notices of their botanical contemporaries. Philadelphia: Lindsay & Blakiston, 1849.
Marshall, Humphry, and Lézermes. Catalogue alphabétique des arbres et arbrisseaux: qui croissent naturellement dans les Etats-Unis de l'Amérique Septentrionale, arrangés selon les systême de Linne; contenant les caractères particuliers qui distinguent les genres auxquels ils sont rapportés, avec des descriptions claires & familières de leur manière de croître, de leur forme extérieure, &c., & leurs différentes espèces & variétes. A Paris: Chez Cuchet, libraire, rue & hotel Serpente, 1788.
Pleasants, Henry. Three scientists of Chester County: by Henry Pleasants, Jr. [n. p., 1936].